Guide to the United Methodist Church Records, 1784-1984, bulk 1800-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United Methodist Church records 1784-1984 bulk 1800-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United Methodist Church (U.S.)
48.8 linear feet Extent: 5922 Items
The Methodist Church in N.C. began about 1772 with the first Methodist preaching at Currituck Court House. In 1785, the Christmas Conference was held in Baltimore, Md., establishing the Methodist Episcopal Church (MEC) in the United States. At that time, N.C. territory was encompassed within the Va. and S.C. Conferences. In 1824, the Holston Conference formed, including sections of N.C. west of the Appalachian Mountains. In 1836 the N.C. Conference was formed. Between 1844-1845, pro-slavery dissenters left the MEC and formed the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS). A majority of N.C. churches joined the MECS, significantly reducing the number of churches in the MEC. What had been the N.C. Conference and Holston Conference, MEC, became N.C. Conference and Holston Conference, MECS. Between 1845 and 1865, there was no official N.C. Conference, MEC. However, in 1869, the N.C. Conference of the MEC re-formed, which included the entire state of N.C. In 1870, southern and western piedmont counties moved from the S.C. Conference of the MECS to the N.C. Conference, MECS. At this time, the N.C. Conference, MECS, included all N.C. counties except those west of the Appalachian mountains. In 1890, the Western N.C. Conference was organized, composed of the western part of the N.C. Conference, MEC, and territory west of the Blue Ridge Mountains that had been in the Holston Conference, MEC. In 1939 the MECS, MEC, and Methodist Protestant Church (MPC) merged to become the Methodist Church (MC), and the Western N.C. Conference and N.C. Conference of the MC formed, composed of white ministers and congregations. At the same time, the Central Jurisdiction of the MC formed, composed of African-American congregations and ministers. In 1968, all conferences and jurisdictions of the MC and the Evangelical United Brethren Church merged into the United Methodist Church (UMC). The United Methodist Church Records are comprised primarily of bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes that document the administrative life of church units (circuits, charges, and churches) in the N.C. Conference (1784-1974, bulk 1841-1919) and the Western N.C. Conference (1884-1962, bulk 1893-1932) of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS). Counties in N.C. represented in the collection include Alamance, Ashe, Bladen, Burke, Caswell, Catawba, Chatham, Cleveland, Dare, Davidson, Durham, Forsyth, Gates, New Hanover, Iredell, Lincoln, Perquimans, Randolph, Rowan, Yadkin, and Wake. However, this collection does not include complete runs of any set of bound minutes, correspondence, or other documentation for any N.C. county or district. There are also bound volumes of N.C. Conference, MECS, district conference minutes (1866-1939); financial, administrative, and legal records for the Board of Missions and Church Extension of the Western N.C. Conference, MECS (1909-1952); bound journals of annual conference meetings of the N.C. Conference, MECS (1838-1913); as well as some district, conference, and national records for non-N.C. conferences and for the MECS and the Methodist Episcopal Church (MEC). National records include correspondence and financial records from the American Mission in North Africa, MEC (1909-1952). Although the entire collection dates from 1784-1984, the bulk of the material dates from 1800-1940.
RL.00891
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, a few of the original materials in the collection are restricted except for use under direct staff supervision. Patrons must use photocopies of originals.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rubenstein Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The United Methodist Church Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1948-1997.
Historical Note
Although this collection contains records primarily from the N.C. and Western N.C. Conferences of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS), and national records from both the MECS and the Methodist Episcopal Church (MEC), this chronology is provided as an aid to understanding the context of the records contained in this collection.
1772 First Methodist preaching in North Carolina at Currituck Court House in northeastern N.C.
1774 Petersburg Circuit extends into N.C.
1776 Carolina Circuit forms and is located in the north central part of N.C.
1780 Yadkin Circuit forms out of the Pittsylvania Circuit in Va. and is located in the present area of the Western N.C. Conference
1783 Salisbury Circuit forms out of the Yadkin Circuit
1780s Preachers from S.C. circuits extend their range into western N.C.
1785 Christmas Conference held in Baltimore, Md., establishing the Methodist Episcopal Church (MEC) in the United States
1785 Virginia Conference, MEC, forms; exists until 1837
1787 South Carolina Conference, MEC, forms; exists until 1844
1824 Holston Conference, MEC, forms out of the Western Conference, which includes the section of N.C. west of the Appalachian mountains; exists until 1844
1828 Dissenters over Bishops' powers leave the Methodist Episcopal Church and form the Methodist Protestant Church (MPC); MPC exists until 1939 North Carolina Conference, MPC, forms, which overlaps geographically with the part of N.C. that was in the Va. Conference of the MEC; conference exists until 1939
1836 North Carolina Conference of the MEC forms out of the Va. Conference, composed from the northern half of N.C. to the Appalachian mountains in the West; territory overlaps with the N.C. Conference of the MPC
1838 First session of the North Carolina Conference, MEC, is held in Greensboro
1844-1845 Dissenters leave the MEC over slavery and form the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS); majority of N.C. churches join the MECS N.C. Conference and the Holston Conference also join the MECS MECS exists until 1939
1845-1865 No official MEC conference in N.C.
1850 Sandhills region of southeastern N.C. moves from the S.C. Conference, MECS, into the N.C. Conference, MECS
1865 Holston Conference of the MEC forms again, which includes the section of N.C. west of the Appalachian mountains; exists until 1878
1867 Virginia-North Carolina Mission Conference of the MEC forms, which includes the northern half of N.C. to the Appalachian mountains in the West; comprises both African American and white members Exists until 1869
1869 N.C. Conference of the MEC forms out of the Va.-NC. Mission Conference, which includes the entire state of N.C.; exists until 1878
1870 Southern and western piedmont counties move from the S.C. Conference, MECS, to the N.C. Conference, MECS; the N.C. Conference is now composed of all N.C. counties except territory to the west of the Appalachian mountains, which remain in the Holston Conference of the MECS
1870 A separate Methodist Church, the Colored Methodist Church in America (CMCA), forms out of the MECS for all African-American members; exists until 1956
1879 White members of the N.C. Conference of the MEC and the N.C. part of the Asheville District of the Holston Conference, MEC, form the Southern Central Conference, MEC; exists until 1880
1879 N.C. Black Conference of the MEC forms out of the Va.-NC. Mission Conference; exists until 1939
1881 Name of Southern Central Conference, MEC, changes to Blue Ridge Conference, MEC; name remains through 1912
1890 Western North Carolina Conference of the MECS forms out of the western part of the N.C. Conference of the MECS and the N.C. part of the Holston Conference, MECS; exists until 1939
1896 Blue Ridge Conference, MEC, divides into the Atlantic Mission Conference in the eastern half of the state and the Blue Ridge Conference in the western half; both conferences exist until 1912
1912 Blue Ridge and Atlantic Mission Conferences of the MEC merge to form the Blue Ridge-Atlantic Conference of the MEC, which is composed of all of N.C., seven counties in southeastern Va., and twelve counties in S.C.
1913 Boundaries of the Blue Ridge-Atlantic Conference of the MEC change to include only N.C.
1939 MECS, MEC, and MPC merge into the Methodist Church (MC) Western N.C. Conference and N.C. Conference of the MC forms, composed of white ministers and congregations CMCA continues as a separate denomination
1939 Central Jurisdiction of the MC forms, composed of African-American congregations and ministers; exists until 1964
1956 CMCA changes name to Christian Methodist Episcopal Church
1965 North Carolina-Virginia Conference Central Jurisdictions, MC, form from the Central Jurisdiction, MC; jurisdictions exist until 1968
1968 MC and the Evangelical United Brethren Church merge into the United Methodist Church (UMC) North Carolina-Virginia Central Jurisdictions merge into either the Western N.C. Conference or the N.C. Conference, UMC
Resources used to write this history include Methodism in the Upper Cape Fear Valley, Chapter 1: The North Carolina Conference, 1838, by C. Franklin Grill (Nashville, Tenn.: The Parthenon Press, 1966) and History of the Western North Carolina Annual Conference, by Joseph W. Lasley, Southeastern Jurisdiction Historical Society Proceedings June 30-July 3, 1989 (Lake Junaluska, N.C., [1989]). See the information folder for this collection in the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library for a copy of the latter resource.
Collection Overview
The United Methodist Church Records are comprised primarily of bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes that document the administrative life of smaller church units (circuits, charges, and churches) within the N.C. Conference (1784-1974, bulk 1841-1919) and the Western N.C. Conference (1884-1962, bulk 1893-1932) of the Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS). Counties in N.C. represented in the collection include Alamance, Ashe, Bladen, Burke, Caswell, Catawba, Chatham, Cleveland, Dare, Davidson, Durham, Forsyth, Gates (also Va.), New Hanover, Iredell, Lincoln, Perquimans (also Va.), Randolph, Rowan, Yadkin, and Wake. There are also bound volumes of N.C. Conference, MECS, district conference minutes (1866-1939); financial, administrative, and legal records for the Board of Missions and Church Extension of the Western N.C. Conference, MECS (1909-1952); bound journals of annual conference meetings of the N.C. Conference, MECS (1838-1913); as well as some district, conference, and national records for non-N.C. conferences and for the MECS and the Methodist Episcopal Church (MEC). The national records include correspondence--especially to and from J. H. Colpais Purdon--and financial records from the American Mission in North Africa, MEC (1909-1952); and correspondence, minutes, reports, and printed material documenting the planning for the reunification of the MEC and the MECS (1906-1916, 1932-1939), especially hymnal revision.
In addition to the quarterly conference and district conference minutes, the N.C. Conference and Non-N.C. Conference Series include membership, Sunday School, abstinence society, and susbscription and class lists (Buckhorn, Currituck, Forsyth, and Haw River Circuits); plans and maps of circuits (Currituck, Forsyth, and Holly Springs Circuits); notes, drawings, and inventories of church buildings and furniture (Iredell and Roanoke Circuits); and handwritten responses of the Eastern Shore of Virginia to the MEC split, some written by William Gwynn Coe. The Historical Sketches Series includes land deeds for churches and correspondence written by or pertaining to Francis Asbury and Thomas Coke; and some information about churches with mixed-race congregations. Although the entire collection dates from 1784-1984, the bulk of the material dates from 1800-1940.
This collection does not include complete runs of any set of bound minutes, correspondence, or other documentation for any N.C. county or district. Thus, it does not provide a full view of the activities of the Methodist Church in N.C. However, for both the N.C. and Western N.C. Conferences, some districts, circuits, and counties are well-represented. These include, in the N.C. Conference, MECS, the Durham District (1885-1927), Elizabeth City District (1911-1922), Raleigh District (1914-1915 and 1935-1939), and Wilmington District (1866-1898); and Bath Circuit (Beaufort Co., 1849-1894), Dare Circuit (Dare Co., 1859-1903), Fifth Street Charge/Church/Station (New Hanover Co., 1844-1905), Gates Circuit (Gates Co., 1784-1911), Iredell Circuit (Iredell Co., 1823-1873), Leasburg Circuit (Caswell Co., 1883-1930), North Gates Circuit (Gates Co., 1884-1937), Pasquotank Circuit (Pasquotank Co., 1852-1906), Pittsboro Circuit (Chatham Co., 1854-1943), and Yanceyville Circuit (Caswell Co., 1844-1902). In the Western N.C. Conference the Asheville District (1912-1916) and Winston-Salem District (1924-1935) are well-documented, along with Alamance Circuit (Alamance Co., 1893-1908), First Methodist Church/Station (Lincoln Co., 1902-1962), Jefferson Circuit (Ashe Co., 1893-1932), Morganton Circuit (Burke Co., 1889-1932), Polkville Circuit (Cleveland Co., 1911-1927), and Randolph Circuit/Charge (Randolph Co., 1893-1930).
Arranged in five series and three indexes: National Records Series; Non-N.C. Conference Records Series; N.C. Conference Records Series; Western N.C. Conference Records Series; Historical Sketches Series;Circuit, Charge, and Station Index;Church and Mission Index; and Baptismal Records, MECS, Index.
The National Records Series comprises national-level records from the MEC (1820-1952) and the MECS (1857-1939), including correspondence and financial records from the American Mission in North Africa of the MEC (1909-1952), especially correspondence to and from Joseph Cooksey, Edwin Frease, and Joseph Purdon (1909-1925). The MECS national records comprise primarily correspondence, minutes, reports, and printed material documenting the planning for the reunification of the MEC and the MECS (1906-1916, 1932-1939), especially hymnal revision.
The Non-N.C. Conference Records Series consists primarily of bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes for circuits, charges, and churches in the Baltimore, North Georgia, South Carolina, Virginia and other Conferences, especially those in Lumpkin Co., Ga.; Marion Co., S.C.; and Gates and Loudoun Cos., Va. Circuit, charge, and church-level records include a classbook of the Pleasant Hill Society (1851-1879, Dallas Co., Ala.); a hand-drawn map from the 1800s of the Holly Springs Circuit (unknown Co., Miss.); and a history of the formation of the Methodist Protestant Church in Maryland, 1833. There are conference-level records only for the Virginia and Wisconsin Conferences and these include an 1815 list of ministers serving Virginia Conference districts and circuits, as well as a group of hand-written "responses" of the Eastern Shore of Virginia to the Methodist Episcopal Church split (1864-1866).
The N.C. Conference Records Series comprises primarily bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes that document the administrative life of circuits, charges, churches, missions, and stations of the N.C. Conference, MECS, in the eastern and central counties of North Carolina, particularly Bladen, Caswell, Chatham, Dare, Durham, Gates, New Hanover, Perquimans, and Wake, but also including other counties (1784-1974). In addition, the series includes bound journals of annual conference meetings for the N.C. Conference of the MECS (1838-1913), as well as bound volumes of district conference minutes and quarterly conference minutes for, among other districts, the Durham, Elizabeth City, Raleigh, and Wilmington Districts of the N.C. Conference of the MECS (1866-1939).
The Western N.C. Conference consists primarily of bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes and church registers that document the administrative life of MECS and Methodist Church (MC) circuits, charges, churches, missions, and stations in the western and west central counties of North Carolina (1893-1932). Counties include Alamance, Ashe, Burke, Catawba, Cleveland, Davidson, Forsyth, Iredell, Lincoln, Randolph, Rowan, and Yadkin, among others. The series also includes financial, administrative, and legal records for the Board of Missions and Church Extension of the Western N.C. Conference of the MECS (1909-1952), as well as quarterly conference and district conference minutes and trustees minutes for districts within the Western N.C. Conference including, among others, the Asheville and Winston-Salem districts (1912-1935).
The Historical Sketches Series comprises primarily historical and biographical information solicited from N.C. ministers about themselves, their churches, circuits, and counties in 1879 by H. T. Hudson and in 1895 by an unknown person. Also includes earlier and later sketches, especially typescript or handwritten articles, essays, or sermons on Methodism in N.C.
The Circuit, Charge, and Station Index lists in alphabetical order all circuit, charge, and station names found in this finding aid and gives their box location. It excludes circuits, charges, or stations already listed in the Historical Sketches Series. This index is not an inclusive list of all circuits, charges, and stations that may be found in this collection. Users are encouraged to consult the quarterly conference minutes for the geographical area or county in which they are interested to find additional references to other circuits, charges, and stations.
The Church and Mission Index lists in alphabetical order all church and mission names found in this finding aid and gives their box location. It excludes churches or missions already listed in the Historical Sketches Series. This index is not an inclusive list of all churches and missions that may be found in this collection. Users are encouraged to consult the quarterly conference minutes for the geographical area or county in which they are interested to find additional references to other churches and missions.
The Baptismal Records, MECS Index is arranged in three groupings: N.C. Conference, Western N.C. Conference, and Va. Conference, and within these groupings, the records are listed by county. This index was compiled in 1968 and does not include any additions to the collection since that date.
There are also Related Materials, which list Methodist Church-related collections (but not all collections with Methodism as a subject area) in the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library at Duke University and in the Duke University Archives. This section also notes which records in this collection are available on microfilm. Like this collection, the related materials are organized by series and then by subseries name.
Related Material
Related Material to the Non-N.C. Conferences
Kentucky Conference
Unknown Co., Lexington First Church, Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1809-1841 (not entire volume) (Lexington District). Available on microfilm, #189-1-1.
Mississippi Conference
Unknown Co., White Sands, Westville, and Mt. Carmel Circuits, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1835-1877 (Choctaw District). Available on microfilm, #190-1-1.
Related Material in the N.C. Conference
Conference Records
Journals, 1838-1923. Available on microfilm, #191-1-1 to 191-5-1/
N.C. Conference Historical Society, Letter on Society formation, 1874. Found in William Clark Doub Papers.
District Records
Rockingham District, Presiding Elder's Minutes, 1892. Found in Marquis L. Wood Records and Papers, (Duke University Archives), Box 3, Folder 15.
Rockingham District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1891-1893. Found in Marquis L. Wood Records and Papers.
Wilmington District, District Conference Records, beginning 1897. Found in the N.C. Conference of the United Methodist Church Media Center, Raleigh, N.C.
Circuit, Charge, and Church Records
Bladen Co., Elizabeth Circuit (Fayetteville, Rockingham, and Wilmington Districts), Church Registers Nos. 1-2, 1888-1930; Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1908-1949; and Papers, 1926 and 1942. Available on microfilm, #191-7-1.
Chatham, Moore and Carteret Cos., Deep River Circuit (Hillsboro District) and Trent Circuit (New Bern District), Class Book, 1871-1872. Found in William F. Clegg Papers.
Dare Co., Roanoke Island and Dare Mission/Circuit (Suffolk and other districts), Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1888-1891. Available on microfilm, #192-1-1 and #192-1-2
Forsyth Co., Forsyth Circuit (Salisbury District), Class Book, 1851. Found in William Clark Doub Papers.
Gates Co., Gates Circuit (Elizabeth City and Suffolk, Va. Districts), Church Register, 1784-1887. Available on microfilm, #192-2-1.
Gates Co., North Gates Circuit (Elizabeth City, Murfreesboro, Va., and Suffolk, Va. Districts), Church Register, 1884-1937. Available on microfilm, #192-2-1.
Halifax Co., Roanoke and Littleton Circuits (Warrenton District), Methodist Church Records, 1860-1905 and undated Found in Edward Alston Thorne Papers.
Randolph Co., Randolph Circuit (Greensboro and Trinity College Districts), Quarterly Conference Minutes (original copy), 1888-1892. Found in the Mt. Vernon United Methodist Church, Trinity, N.C.
Richmond Co., Rockingham Station (Fayetteville District), Pastor's Visiting and Memorandum Book, 1889-1890. Found in Marquis L. Wood Records and Papers (Duke University Archives), Box 3, Folder 15.
Mulitple Cos., deed abstracts of Methodist churches in 56 counties in the NC Conference. Joseph W. Watson, author. Available on microfilm, number M 6626
Unknown Co., Davidson Circuit (Greensboro District), Plan of Davidson Circuit and Preacher's Memorandum, 1860-1861. Found in John Wesley Lewis Papers.
Unknown Co., Duke's Chapel Methodist Church. Found in Rosa Belvin Papers.
Unknown Co., Franklin Circuit (Va.), Class Book, 1851-1852. Found in John Wesley Lewis Papers.
Unknown Co., Green Valley Mission (Va.), Notebook, 1870-1878. Found in Washington Varner Papers.
Unknown Co., Hardy Circuit (West Va.), Notebook, 1870-1878. Found in Washington Varner Papers.
Unknown Co., Pastor's Books, 1903-1934, for Grimesland and Vanceboro, Spring Hope and Mt. Pleasant, Mt. Pleasant, Richmond, Robeson, Chadbourn, Jonesboro, Creedmoor, Durham and Mt. Tirzah Circuits. Found in Benjamin E. Stanfield Papers.
Unknown Co., plan of Tar River Circuit. Found in John Wesley Lewis Papers.
Related Material in the Western N.C. Conference
Conference Records
Key to Map of the Western N.C. Conference. Found in John C. Kilgo Records and Papers (Duke University Archives), Lectures, Folder 96.
Western N.C. Conference (generally), Methodist Board of Education, and Women's Society of Christian Service (Mary Eskridge King). Found in Carl Howie King Papers.
[Note re: Lake Junaluska]
Related Material on Historical Sketches
Methodism
Writings on the History of Methodism in N.C., 1876-1892. Found in Marquis L. Wood Records and Papers (Duke University Archives), Box 3, Folder 27
Subject Headings